Hello and welcome.
And we're going to present
four presentations on community and games.
I'm Rachel Kerr
and I'm presenting on community in Games
and how it alters
perception and experiences during gameplay
as presentation
will focus on the asymmetric horror
game Dead by Daylight
as a case study to demonstrate
how community can alter the intended
experience from its original design
through expectations
created over time and communicated
through different social media sites.
For this,
I will begin with a brief overview
of daylight, which I will refer to as DVD
for the remainder of the presentation,
and then I will discuss the community
aspects in how they form and influence
play for both sides of the screen.
DVD is an asymmetric horror game,
meaning that it is a multiplayer game
where players are divided
into two opposing sides
with unequal numbers
of the leaves and objectives.
In DVD, the players within the community
divide themselves into two distinct camps,
each that have their own playstyle,
objectives, and when condition survivors
arrive at a trial in four person teams
equipped with up to four perks
and one item
that will assist them
in completing their objective,
as if I was only objective is to escape.
And while many survivors
also include the added
task of aiding their fellow players,
it is not something that alters a service
win condition
or how they go about achieving it.
So I play the match in third person,
keeping an eye out while carrying out
their objectives.
Killers,
on the other hand, are only one to a match
and are for the most part stuck
with the first person perspective.
With a handful of exceptions, each killer
comes equipped with a signature weapon
and ability that can drastically affect
how players play through the trial.
The killer's task is to find, catch,
hook, and eventually kill each survivor
before they can open the exit gates
at the end of the trial and escape
during a match outside of two emotes,
a point in a compare motion available
only to survivors.
There are no built
in methods of communication.
DVD instead limits in game
communication to the brief lobby chat only
available survivors, and the endgame chat
where survivors and killers can interact.
Despite this, the community has over time
created a set of rules and expectations
that allow for some communication
during the match, even when solo cueing,
some are as simple as crouching twice
to thank a fellow survivor for healing.
A bit more complicated in the act
of leaving a gift for a killer player
who might not be in on the rules.
As players have crafted these rulesets,
they have also struggled
to define what they consider toxicity
within the community.
Toxicity, per Merriam-Webster, describes
behavior, attitudes, or environments
that are emotionally, mentally,
or physically draining and harmful,
and as players within the community debate
what they consider to be toxic
that often returns to debate on
what is fair.
Despite DVDs one v4 system,
which clearly intends to create an unfair
match as this debate continues, often
with each side declaring different actions
within a match to be toxic
or at the very least, a little rude.
Players within the community
turn towards each other
and begin to determine their own rules.
Within the small bubbles,
they're communicating in rules
that other players are then unaware of,
and that newer players
will have never even heard of.
This creates somewhat of a feedback loop.
As a player
that's been in the game for a while,
takes offense at someone it's
something they've determined to be toxic,
such as hitting on hook,
the action of the killer,
hitting a survivor player
after they've been hooked,
which is no mechanical use.
The newer player is still testing
what they can and cannot do in a match.
In the endgame chat,
the older player might then berate
the newer player
for their perceived toxicity, often
without explaining what exactly
they're complaining about,
and the player might respond
to perceived hostility in kind.
Now, the entire match is viewed
as a bad or toxic experience on both sides
and all players, and obviously only one
player was aware of the rules
that they have created
outside of the game, with only a fraction
of the game's players.
To better
understand how these rules are created
within the community, I looked at where
the community chooses to discuss them.
The most prominent place for debate
is Twitter or X,
though TikTok is also fairly popular
in the majority of the authorities, people
who are deferred to on Twitter have large
followings on both TikTok and Twitch.
These communities often form around one
side of the game, with survivor players
butting heads with killer
and both debating back and forth
on which in-game action
by either side is considered toxic
within the DVD community.
Like any video game communities,
there are often those
who are considered authorities
or at least have some influence, either
with behavior, the company that owns
the game, or the community itself.
Often they have a presence
on all three of the sites I've mentioned,
and these are the players
who have the most influenced
for a variety of reasons,
and therefore the most influence
on how players interact
with the game themselves.
Creators such as Austria
and Hines are some of the most
well known in the community, considered
authorities on the game, with the builds
they make often becoming
well played and commonly seen play styles
such as Hines recent
hex Jason build a killer build
revolving around
to inconvenience and slow down survivor
players, and the highly awaited Jason.
Both creators have websites
they use, as well as their Twitch streams,
to make these builds accessible
to players.
For older players,
this generally isn't all that different
from making a build of their own,
and doesn't exactly alter their experience
in any perceivable way,
but for newer players
who are inexperienced in the game,
this can be a very different experience.
Is there introduced to new concepts
that they don't always understand
and often mechanics
they have never interacted with
similarly, hence has created a call out
system, something that is entirely useless
in a solo queue setting.
But when playing with comms between
friends, often over things like discord,
it can entirely change
the experience of a trial
as a player, as plays refer to a system
that is often used in competitive
games, players begin to consider
DVD in a more competitive light.
These competitive players
are an interesting
example of community perception
altering play,
as DVD itself has no competitive mode
and therefore no competitive matchmaking.
Instead, they operate off of a system
referred to as MMR.
MMR acts as a behind the scenes
balance for players, as there placed
in matches meant to ensure the players
remain in lobbies of a similar skill set.
Self is not something a player can see.
There is no rank system
such as you would see in a game
like Overwatch or Valorant,
and only the idea of
working in the background
kind of leads to this competitiveness.
Competitive play is often
used as both an excuse and an accusation
for actions in game.
The portions of the player base
have deemed toxic,
as players make use of mechanics
that are not technically outside
of the expected experience
within the design of the game.
Many of these are considered
toxic, less because they are objectively
unfair players in the game,
and more because they do not allow players
to complete
what they believe is the expected game.
A killer tunneling or eliminating
a single player as quickly as possible
despite other players interference,
often works to the rest of the survivors
players favor, but is considered
unsportsmanlike as it forces
one player out of a match much earlier
than the other. For
this perception
that DVD is not a competitive game
but can be played
competitively often leads
to further debate, as killer players argue
that the tactics survivors deem
toxic are necessary for competitive play,
and then you go back and forth on the
whether or not competitive
play exists at all.
This further adds to the community's
favorite debate
what is and isn't fair and game,
with survivors arguing that killer tactics
and killers arguing that the survivor
with or survive with friends
a four stack is an unfair advantage.
In fact, a direct example of
this would be the streamer
Momo Seventh, who lost his 1992
win blight streak
to a swift of players and blamed it
entirely on the fairness debate.
Okay, so moving on a little, I'm
going to shift gears.
So it's getting perception and how players
experience is often altered by it,
but with a focus less on the mechanics
and more on the characters.
At this current moment,
you could load into a DVD lobby
as David
King, a behavior original on the far
right, and be met with Quintin Smith,
Leon S Kennedy, and Laurie Strode.
Each of these characters are available
to those fulfilling the survivor role
in a trial, along with 49 other distinct
individual characters.
As characters have been added to
and on occasion removed from the game,
different stereotypes have formed, often
tied to a specific character
and the reference expected of them
in a match and on occasion outside of it.
These experiences.
These expectations often color
how players interact
with the match, with players
willing to give up or go next.
On occasions they feel the player
they've been matched with
might not fit the skill level they want.
One of the most common examples of
it is not every sable, but always a sable.
Take sable words name out and character
created behavior and plays it
with almost any other survivor.
And it's been said,
some of the most well known legendary
characters skins connected to one survivor
with their own name model change,
and often voice lines are even included.
As a result.
Sable Ward has a reputation,
but so too does Leon S Kennedy,
a reputation that has nothing to do
with the Resident Evil games here
in, and everything to do with the player
perception within the game.
On the other hand,
really honest Kennedy has a reputation
as a bad player who will leave you to die.
Chris Redfield
also has a reputation as a player
who will not leave their teammates behind.
The interesting factor
in the reputation of Chris
is that it is based on the games
he originates in, and how players
believe that those who buy
and then use Chris will commit
to following his Resident Evil
characterization.
Despite
having such a low opinion of Leon Kennedy,
the survivor of the Chris is linked
to, this is entirely title.
Players discuss each character
outside of the game.
Nine times out of 10 billion, Kennedy
you interact with in-game
will be just like any other player,
but that 10th time is the one
that gets discussed.
It's the clip that goes viral,
and it's the one
everyone will be referencing
for the next few months.
On the other hand,
the clips of Chris Redfield going back for
the save will get the same treatment
compared to a clip of the player
leaving another survivor to die.
In a similar vein, killers have their own
perception built around different.
Oh my gosh,
different killers over
time, from the toxic Carnegie,
the ghoul to the friendly ghost face.
For example,
a pig player
might come across a confusing sight,
a survivor crouching towards them
and occasionally doing the way you emote.
For an experienced player,
this could only mean one thing,
and it's the biggest feeling generous?
They might grant the request,
crouching up to the survivor player.
To allow them to point at their face
and boop the snoot, something survivor
players commonly hope they can do.
And faced with the saw character
as a slasher of the match,
similar experiences
might be seen with the likes of Dracula
and the Xenomorph, whereas an experience
is an experience like that on a killer
such as the clown would be baffling.
As a result,
both survivor and Killer players
can instead financial
spending a match attempting
to understand what the other side
is trying to do based off of these rules
that they have learned over time
from things like TikTok,
Twitter, and Twitch, and understanding
how the community discusses this
and this discourse leads to altered
expectations,
allows us to better understand
how these rules form
and how the community affects play,
and more than just player account,
with the caveat
that for this presentation,
I did not look into behavior
and how their mechanics and decisions also
alter the gameplay effect in experience.
Thank you.
So hi everybody
I'm Cameron Irby I'm a lecturer
at the University of Texas at Dallas.
And today I'm presenting Dead or Alive.
Service by daylight is a dark
mirror of the gaming industry.
When we were proposing this panel,
I proposed
looking at it from the opposite side
of my co-presenter, Rachel.
And as you mentioned,
you didn't go too much into the mechanics
and how those affect behavior.
That's where I'll take catch in.
So I'm going to be looking at
the strenuous relationship
between David Daylight's players.
It's developer behavior Interactive,
and how those can be used as ciphers
of a sort to better understanding
the state of the gaming industry today.
As a quick note,
as a game studies and fan studies
scholar, I'm not exactly looking at Dead
by Daylight as just a spectator.
Over my years of playing this game,
and dear Lord, I've played a few years,
my interest has grown beyond getting good
to wanting a deeper understanding
of its systems, its narrative framing,
and how it's maintained its popularity.
Thanks and thanks to and in spite
of the measures taken to keep it alive.
As such, I'm interrogating my experience
of play through ludo textual analysis,
a method that Paul Booth describes
as a combination of literary
and media analysis that includes
a very important participatory element.
Although one can glean a lot
from observing just from the outside,
a situated experience of playing Dead
by Daylight helps to reveal
how its many pieces come together
through the act of play.
My research I was also drawing from Zuber
and Larson's concept of the fan
producer relationship from their book
fandom at the crossroads, which describes
how modern cultural producers
like Behavior Interactive collaborate
with their fans, in this case
their players, while actively shaping the
object of their fandom, dead by daylight
to both appease and exploit them.
Which I say in a capitalistic sense here.
Through these lenses,
I argue that By Daylight operates
as a microcosm of the commercial games
industry today, offering a dark
mirror to examine both its appeal
and its more monstrous edges.
To start.
As some of you may be aware.
Last week, Sony announced
the end of physical description
for the PlayStation console,
with Microsoft Xbox
rumored to follow shortly.
These developments stoked
the ire of many, yet
this is far from a new trend
for the commercial games industry.
For years, digital storefronts
like steam remind buyers
that they're not purchasing games, but
licenses to download the files, licenses
that heavily restrict access
and can be revoked at any time.
In other words, the end of physical discs
marks a continued transformation
from games as products to games
as a service like MMOs before them.
Games as a service,
more commonly known as live service games,
popularize the idea of a forever
game for players and game makers alike.
If players spend money on the game,
the producers can theoretically
reinvest the profits back into the game
to once again meet demand.
So on and so forth.
This concept has been,
and repeatedly, often
presented as an infinite money glitch.
But because development
can theoretically continue ad infinitum,
there is one catch
if so long as the game is profitable.
This promise of infinite growth
and exponential wealth has led
numerous studios
across the commercial games industry
to create thousands of live services,
many of which are no longer with us.
This small selection of now defunct
live service games reveals the precarity
inherent to shifting from games
as products to games as a service.
Games require a massive upfront cost
to create them, a cost
that they must recoup rather quickly.
The product based model
creates a game for retail,
then uses the profits
garnered to create the next one.
Live service games, in contrast, ask
players to subsidize their development,
typically through the purchase
of exclusive in-game content.
Many more live service games
than these have failed to immediately
capture market of players
willing to foot the bill,
and as a result, they stopped being well.
A live service
simply by managing to survive
for ten years, dead by Daylight
can be considered an example
of a successful live service game.
For now, though tempting to attribute Dead
by Daylight success to sheer luck,
Behavior, interactive
takes care to construct a fan producer
relationship that can sustain it.
One that has been refined over the past
decade
to exceed both player expectations
and competing live service games.
Notably, this is a shared experience.
The players of Dead by Daylight helped to
shape the game alongside its developers.
For now, I'll be briefly touching on
a few examples of Depot Daylight's
live service elements to highlight
how behavior frames this relationship.
Starting off with the narrative.
As my co-presenter mentioned,
you can have some very wild combinations
of characters, but the actual frame
narrative for the game
has this thin, tongue in cheek
reasoning for its characters
to be engaging with one another.
All of these characters
have been whisked away from their worlds
to this nightmarish Valhalla,
and must either survive in the hopes
of escape, or start sacrificing one
another to appease the entity.
Who's the entity we don't know.
All this blank space gives fans
a room to fill in the details
and to construct their own understandings
of how the story World of Dead
by Daylight works.
The story will also easily elides
any questions raised by, say,
Nicolas Cage,
the actor teaming up with Laura Croft,
the video game character against Pyramid
Head, who's from a different video game
in the Hawkins lab from Stranger Things.
It gets a little weird, a
little little crazy,
and it's something that
the players accept as a given.
And although the game does
feature its own original characters
and occasionally introduce new law to
further reinforce the general story world,
all the narrative editions work toward
a status quo one no one ever escapes.
No one ever really dies.
This avoids
the years of law and story problem
that MMO such as Final Fantasy 14 face,
allowing new players
to jump in and returning players
to feel like they never left.
But because Pyramid Head Laura Croft,
the actor
Nicolas Cage were active
via licensing deals.
These characters must be purchased
using oryx cells, which themselves
must be purchased with actual cash money
due to these licensing issues.
You run into scenarios where characters
like the Demogorgon from Stranger
Things and Michael Myers
from the Halloween franchise
get intermittently reviewed
from the in-game store.
The insecure nature of these licenses
also helps to generate
a fear of missing out, and players
will rush to unlock these new characters
to unlock their unique perks,
which would take months or years
to unlock otherwise.
In fact, if you take a look at
just the DLC that you can buy on steam.
Dead By Daylight
costs $20 for its base edition,
but if you wanted to have access
to all of the game's characters,
you would need to spend over $300
just to have everything.
Do not get me started on the outfits.
We do not have the time. Though.
Speaking of the perks, pair players
must play continuously
to master the game's many mechanics
and earn in-game currencies
that can be spent on perks, items,
and the less exciting cosmetics.
Effective play,
as determined by the system,
bestows more occurrences
and an increase in player rank.
Conversely, playing ineffectively
according to the system
will cause you to lose rank.
This gameplay loop encourages repeated
play within very narrow boundaries,
and the more time spent increases
the likelihood the players will keep
playing in hopes
of making their time worth it.
Players also need to keep up to date
as frequent tweet updates tweak, add
or remove mechanics as deemed necessary
by behavior for the overall health
of the game, or perhaps for their bottom
line is sometimes hard to tell,
but the patch notes
serve as a discursive space
for the community
to engage with the game itself,
as well as a way for behavior to,
as Rinaldo de Gallo says,
to reassert their dominance in the fan
producer relationship.
Finally, the game works
within a technological assemblage.
This is borrowing from Deleuze
and Guattari here, but
runs on private servers,
uses anti-cheat software
that polices play, and receives
frequent and again against us
patches based on a mix of community
feedback and behavior zone directives.
Players who break these directives,
even accidentally,
could find themselves banned and unable
to access their accounts.
And again, if people purchase
some DLCs and characters,
they still have access
to those characters,
but only if they paid for them.
If you did not pay for them,
you do not have them anymore.
You no longer have access
to their abilities.
Unless, of course, you have some creative
ways around these sorts of things,
such as through the numerous
hacking scandals that the game has had.
To conclude though, as I am
aware of running out of time here,
we can see through these elements
that the fan producer relationship
between Dead by Daylight
and its characters is a complicated
mix of narrative
fragments, rampant monetization,
reinforced gameplay
loops, and technological restraints.
Yet by daylight, power is not absolute.
There is no game without its players,
and the player base
is well aware of their ability to shape
the future of their favorite game.
As such, Behavior Interactive
must work in tandem with its community
to keep its nightmare realm alive.
As the commercial games
industry seeks to recreate and perpetuate
this games as a service model
and in turn, in some cases
hyper accelerated to its logical end,
one could say in this pursuit of profit
over sustainability,
we can also remember that
there is no industry without its players,
or else it too
might become dead by daylight.
Thank you all very much.
I do want to very quickly
show off my citations, and with that,
I think we'll start working and shift
to our next presenter.
Give us just one moment to switch over.
Hello everyone.
I'm going to be shifting gears
to a different game.
So I'm Cheri Tang, and today
I'll be presenting my paper on cooperation
within blood on the Clock Tower,
particularly how players demonstrate
mis and disinformation resiliency.
And for the purposes of this presentation,
I'll be focusing on misinformation
or the unintentional spread
of false information.
So for a brief agenda, I'm
going to explain what the clock tower is.
And then today I'll talk about
one of its game states drunkenness.
And through the game structure,
how it's unlike other social deduction
games by lying to its players,
which resembles misinformation spread.
But instead of spiraling
into an accusatory chaos,
one on the Clock
Tower is a surprisingly cooperative game.
And so I characterized this mindset behind
good team strategies to
then show how this cooperative mindset
relates to third person
effect, to misinformation exposure.
And then I draw connections
to our modern informational landscape.
So what is blood on the clock tower blend?
The Clock Tower is a social deduction game
created and designed by Steven Medway,
published in 2022
by the Ammonium Institute.
So players are separated into two teams
the good Team in blue and the evil
team in red.
And all of this is overseen by
the storyteller player who runs the game.
So the good team must find and execute
the demon to win the game.
So that the demon dies.
Goodwin's and the evil team
must wipe out the entire town and wins.
If just two players are left alive
and at the start of each game, players are
randomly given a secret role, also known
as a character, and these characters
are categorized based on abilities
that are granted to each player
on the good team.
Majority of players will be townsfolk
who have helpful abilities and gather
information, and a few outsiders
who have unhelpful abilities
for their good team,
and the evil team is made up of minions
who use their character abilities
to cause chaos,
assisting their one demon to win the game.
But the Clock Tower is inspired by Mafia
or also known as werewolf,
so it has a day and night phase.
During the day, players
discuss freely in public and private,
and they can nominate to execute
a suspicious player at night
or right before the night,
to which night is
when players are woken up one by one
by the storyteller to gain information,
use their ability or to kill, and
the storyteller keeps track of everything.
So player actions, abilities, deaths
all within the game box
also called the Grimoire.
And when the game ends, the storyteller
retells the story by revealing
what happened in the Grimoire.
Throughout the game, the addition
or script denotes the available characters
within each game, with each addition
having its own theme, strategy, and tone.
So the pictures here are trouble
brewing blood on the Clock Towers,
beginner script.
And in this video, it's
an example of gameplay where each player
has their own character so you can see
blue for good and evil is in red.
Here.
There is an exception of two storytellers
within the center,
and you can imagine the players
when they sit in that line,
connecting into a circle
to create a clock.
Thus plot on the clock tower.
So this trouble brewing character
script shows how the good team players
are uniquely incentivized to gain
and hide information throughout the game,
and as a 5 to 20 player social deduction
game, with each player gaining a secret
ability, it echoes Evan Corners
examination of werewolf
such that blood of the clocktower
gameplay involves a lot of uncertainty
through player unpredictability, hitting
formation, and analytical complexity.
And as much as I would love to,
I won't go into each character ability,
their interactions, or in strategies,
or even the experimental and homebrew
characters outside of the base scripts.
Instead, I'm going to highlight the game
state drunkenness, slash poisoning.
I do talk about the other game
state madness within my paper, but today
I'll be only talking about drunkenness
and how it resembles misinformation.
So blood of the clock tower of lies
to its players, stating in the rulebook
that the storyteller
is allowed to lie to you,
and so it introduces false information
via drunkenness, poisoning.
They essentially mean the same thing.
So you think you have an ability,
but you don't.
In other words, a drunk
player does not know they are drunk,
and I'll just use drunkenness
to refer to this game state from now on.
Usually in social deduction games, players
are presented with infallible data,
or the game at least tries
not to interfere with that data.
So plainly.
In werewolf, if you're told you're
the werewolf, then you are
indeed a werewolf, and you will wake up
at night to choose a player to kill.
Essentially,
what players see is what players get.
But in one little clock tower,
players cannot trust even themselves,
and this is best exemplified
by the outsider, the drunk.
Again,
the drug player won't know they are drunk,
so instead
they'll draw a token from the bag
during the setup and they will think
they are that townsfolk.
But instead the storyteller will mark them
down as the drunk within the grimoire,
changing that player's character.
They are now an outsider, and any ability
or information gained due to
that council role will be arbitrarily
given or simulated by the storyteller.
So drunkenness resembles misinformation
such that drunk players personally receive
false information from the storyteller
and, like misinformation spread,
may unintentionally
and confidently share false information
to their own team, building
worlds and trusts based on faulty data.
And this is similar
to how Naomi Alderman describes
our informational landscape of the 2020s
in her book Don't Burn Anyone at the stake
today, alderman describes
us being in a third informational crisis.
She likens the mechanical
and psychological impact
of digital communication
to previous info revolutions,
like that of the Gutenberg printing press.
So while we're faced with echo chambers
of social media
and its enormous ways of information,
we settle for easy explanations,
double down on our perspectives, and deem
those on opposing sides as morally wrong.
Yet blood on the clock tower players
cooperate because of drunkenness,
and their cooperative mindset
is demonstrated by how players
caveat themselves with the phrase
but I might be drunk,
and this appears as them also saying
I think you're drunk, or, well,
they could be drunk, so on and so forth.
And this phrasing shows how players
counteract a third person effect
to misinformation exposure.
The third person effect is a mass
communications research theory that states
people are cognitively biased
to perceive others as more susceptible
to media effects such as false news,
propaganda, and persuasive messaging.
The phrasing what I might be drunk shows
that blood on the clock tower players
recognize their own susceptibility
to misinformation, closing
that perceptual gap of the third person
effect, so they'll often remind themselves
and others of drunkenness
before jumping to conclusions.
New and experienced players
will refer to the script,
pointing out to character abilities
that cause drunkenness when they encounter
conflicting, conflicting information,
and players will open themselves up
to different possibilities,
even if it contradicts something
that they gained personally
or from a socially trustworthy player.
All in all, social
players understand their own
susceptibility to false info
and are willing to be wrong.
So I found that this willingness
characterizes blood on the clock tower's
cooperative behavior.
Unlike other social deduction games,
which often spiral into an accusatory
chaos, players
prioritize trust and communication
rather than hunting people down,
and this is resembled in the good team
strategies,
so they will build worlds, in other words,
offering alternative explanations
to a single set of data.
They'll build trust circles,
or a chain of players
who can verify each other's
pings and alignments
rather than following
the most influential person.
And the nomination phase is more
than a way to execute suspicious players,
but instead they'll use it to probe
and hear out other people,
especially if they haven't
talked to each other yet.
And if that person is being quiet.
And in an interview
with the designer creator Steven Medway,
he talks about negative social tools
like intimidation,
saying that those who bully others
into believing
their world will make a fool of themselves
when they are drunk
and often lose the game for their team,
and said those who communicate
well will win the game.
And I found that this this I might be
drunk mindset resembles misinformation.
Resiliency as misinformation poses
a challenge to the modern
informational landscape,
gamified, gamified inoculation programs
expose people to weakened
versions of miss disinformation
and manipulation techniques.
However, these programs
rarely pit players against each other,
lacking in the uncertainty and complexity
that accompanies social deduction games.
So online
browser games like Harmony square,
they lack the large scale
social interaction and player
and predictability like blood on the clock
tower and misinformation.
Escape rooms like Loki's
Loop are segmented into puzzles
with right and wrong solutions, so players
don't sit within the prolonged uncertainty
like in real life.
And one of these escape rooms.
The primary aim of the game
is for people to experience
what it's like to be fooled, and this
actually refers to the third person effect
to which blood on the clock tower
players already demonstrate
that they recognize it,
and they're oriented into this mindset
because of its game state drunkenness
from good time societies.
Video beginners brew New players
said that through blood on the Clock
tower, you're learning your own pitfalls
such that you're learning,
recognizing the way you personally fall
for misinformation.
And as a game.
Blood on the Clock Tower is accessible,
supported by its cooperative player
community.
Experienced players will guide the newbies
teaching lingo and strategies
that best built trust.
There are added rules that are designed
to intentionally include players
that must otherwise be capable, incapable,
and local and online communities emerge
to play with one another.
This is supplemented by actual play,
YouTube creators, and clocktower
conventions.
So this all begs
the question is that I might be drunk.
Drunk mindset helps the good team win
despite misinformation.
What does it look like when we apply
that same mindset to our own lives?
What if after we watch a salient
short form video like a TikTok, Instagram
reel or YouTube short,
we remind ourselves, but I might be drunk.
What if we wonder if that influencer,
despite social cues like confidence
or numbers of followers
and likes, isn't just drunk themselves?
And what have we set?
The times that we are drunk
or are wrong and open ourselves up
to possibilities or experiences, rather
than doubling down for future studies?
I love to see if blood on the clock tower
players already do apply
this mindset in their own lives,
but by laying out how players cooperate
because of drunkenness, I've shown how the
this cooperative mindset resembles
misinformation resiliency,
and I hope this further shows how play
and digital communication interconnect,
thus adding to the ways
we approach the missing disinformation
within our modern informational landscape.
And thank you for listening, and
I'll shift gears for our last presenter.
So I now have to go from hiding off camera
to being on camera.
I'm Monica Evans, I'm
an associate professor here at UT
Dallas, and I am going to go from Cheri's
very positive, uplifting ending and
just ruin it to go something very much.
Not that I'm also talking about something
I'm not supposed to be talking about,
because when I originally joined
this panel, I was interested in how,
let's say, the communities of developers
and players formed around certain
kinds of indie horror games.
And then the more that I got into it,
I realized, because,
of course,
my original background is in literature,
that I was more interested
in what was going on
inside the games than in the communities
of real people around it.
So this is now a presentation
on the fictional communities
that are created inside these games,
and how indie horror developers are using
essentially their non-player characters
to scare their players even further.
So this is maybe everything will be okay
and maybe it won't.
Community,
suspense and dread and indie horror games.
And it is not clicking.
Let's click there.
Now it's clicking excellent.
So I could talk about this
for three hours.
In ten minutes
I will focus on just a little bit of this.
But in short, Indie Haugen
developers are using their communities
of non-player characters or of NPCs to do
a bunch of things across the game space.
Primarily, they're using them to
emphasize the hostility
and the danger of the game space.
They're able to show how a community
can fracture in real time,
in an interactive way,
and these sorts of things
you're not necessarily
going to see only in games.
You'll see these across horror media
in other kinds of areas.
But one of the things that's
really interesting is that indie horror
games are subverting the player's agency
and essentially using the games them.
So everything
that's gotten really interesting about
these has to do
with the interactivity of this space.
So in terms of what
we're talking about here,
I could spend 20 minutes talking
about every single one of these, but
since we are short, I will be talking
mostly about Crow Country.
But since I can't help myself
if there's time,
there'll be a little bit of Slay
the Princess and Signals
and I will definitely take an offshoot
into Subnautica,
which I'll say if you're
just looking at the key art here,
Subnautica is very different
than the other ones of these,
but it is explicitly a horror game,
and I'll talk about
how it gets to that point in a minute.
So very briefly, I'll be talking
about games that are digital
that are primarily single player,
so very different than Dead by Daylight
and are made by small teams
of independent game developers.
So not Triple-A games,
not what we're talking about 500
or 1000 people making the game together,
but teams that are as small as 20,
sometimes as small as four,
sometimes as small as one,
I will acknowledge
that is messy, but here I'm looking
primarily as horror, as an affect,
as something that is an emotional response
to something that scares you.
So not limiting
what I'm looking at to solely survival
horror
games or corridor horrors or roguelikes.
And I'm also not looking at games
that are using,
say, the imagery
and iconography of horror,
but aren't really intended
to scare the games that I'm targeting.
Here are ones that are primarily
trying to scare the player
pretty consistently across the experience,
either with narrative
and mechanics,
or with the interaction, or with both.
And if we had longer,
this is where I'd be quoting
quite a bit of Bernard parents
the world of scary games.
And then lastly, my bias is always to look
at it from the standpoint of a designer
and a developer to say if you are yourself
trying to create a horror game,
trying to create this sort of
emotional fear response,
and you have a group of NPCs in your game,
how can you use them to to better work
towards that goal?
One of the things we talk about
when we talk
design
is the idea of no missed opportunities.
So here's how you can use
the non-player characters in your game.
So sort of to follow through with that.
A couple of things
to say very briefly as well
that since we're
talking about writing game characters,
we'll just acknowledge that writing
the player character is weird.
And without going into identity theory,
the player character is
someone that the player has to be
and has to relate to at the same time,
and that puts them
in kind of an unusual spot.
But when we're dealing with non-player
characters,
the way that you write
them is more similar to other media.
So you want your
your major characters to be well rounded.
You're allowed to have lots
of flat characters in the background
that are meant to sort of
just make the space feel very real.
But there are also major differences
in a lot of those come from interactivity.
So both major NPCs and background NPCs
can have various levels
of artificial intelligence.
They can have their own passing.
Lots of games will dramatically change
what happens depending on how you,
the player, treat your NPCs,
which can lead to various outcomes,
which is sometimes as simple
as choosing to be friends with character
A versus character B.
Sometimes it's actually deciding who lives
and who dies.
I'll note
also that from a practical standpoint,
NPCs are one of the ways that designers
guide the player through the experience
in terms of game mechanics, game goals,
and also fleshing out the game world.
And lastly,
I realize we're talking about
horror games,
but one of the things they do very well
is they make you, the player, fear
death in a medium where death is
by definition, impermanent.
You're always going to respawn,
you're always going to come back.
So fundamentally
the player knows they will not die.
That is absolutely not true of the NPCs.
This was the least spoiler image
I chose to find
because we've been mad about death
for 30 years.
You can't kill the player,
but you can kill the NPCs,
and if your player cares about them,
you can't.
A lot of emotional half out of that.
So short developers can use non-player
characters, and particularly groups
or communities of non-player characters,
as a way to make the world feel real
and a world that you care about.
And from there, we can make that world
also very, very scary.
So very briefly, I'm going to talk about
one of the three ways
in which we can do this,
which is to emphasize the hostility
and danger of the game space.
So broadly, scary games
take place in scary environments.
There are lots of different kinds
of environments
that we can use to
heighten that experience.
I'm going to talk primarily about two.
The first is environments,
and we can see this the history of horror
and the history of Gothic environments
that are scary
because they should be populated
but aren't.
So the abandoned hospital, the abandoned
shopping mall, the abandoned school.
And these environments are uncanny
because of their abandonment.
They're supposed to be full of a thriving,
happy, positive environment.
And they're absolutely not.
The abandoned
hospital has been overused at this point.
I've been in so many derelict hospitals,
so hang on to this for a minute.
We'll come back to it.
The second one,
as a counterpoint, is the environment.
That is scary.
Not because it's been abandoned by humans,
but because it should not have humans
in it at all.
So a great example of
this is the alien ocean in Subnautica.
So very, very briefly,
the premise of Subnautica
is that you are Robinson Crusoe
ING your way through an alien ocean.
The game starts
with the destruction of the ship,
the Aurora,
and you land on this ocean by yourself.
The first 30 minutes of the game,
you have to deal with an environment
that will kill you, the player.
By default it is 95% underwater
and drowning is a major gaming panic.
The environment is in 360 degrees,
so you have to be aware of danger
that can come at you from literally
any angle which humans are not great at.
And you are.
I really wish I hadn't put this image up
because I still have nightmares
about that creature.
This is absolutely the scariest game
I've ever played.
So Nautica is full of an entire ecology
of creatures that consider you nowhere
near the top of the food chain,
and there is no combat system,
so if you see one,
you're pretty much dead.
So the structure of the environment
in Subnautica by itself does a
really good job of emphasizing the horror
and the difficulty of this space.
And this is also, again, that has
no other characters that you ever see,
but you do hear them quite a bit.
So one of the ways that Sonata uses
the community of NPCs to heighten
that horror is with the radio.
So once you've crashed very quickly,
you get access to radio
and you start hearing distress signals
from all of the other survivors
that have made it.
So you're getting essentially voice lines.
You're getting data about where they are,
and the narrative of the game forces
you to go in those directions.
You can't stop and ignore it.
You have to to progress, to go to these
places that the survivors have come to.
So each time you find a life pod,
essentially
you're finding the after effects
of a horror movie that's already happened.
You never see another character
that you hear them trying to survive,
and then you find them after they happen.
So what this does is it emphasizes
both immediately and over the long
term, the horror of the space immediately.
It's this could have been made.
This could have happened to me long term.
It emphasizes the horror,
because those signals will die out,
that as you continually fail to rescue
people, you gradually get to the point
where you're not getting any more signals
in your left all alone.
And I will say, from a technical design
standpoint, I also love this as a
as a choice by the developers,
because part of the reason
to make this choice
that you hear the survivors
that you never managed to see them,
is because they didn't have a character
animator on staff and knew they couldn't
actually create human beings.
But back to the idea of the hostile game
space that should have a lot of people.
So Crow country itself,
it takes place in an abandoned
amusement park, a space that should have
a lot of happy living people in it.
And very quickly, the first thing you run
into is a wounded teenager.
At that.
I will say the game forces you to save.
You cannot but save Arthur mode,
but the way that it presents it
very early, when you don't know
the literacy of the space,
when you're not quite sure
what the game will
and will not allow you to do,
it feels like a very real choice.
You have so right up front,
the game is reminding you
people can die in this space.
It's not necessarily you,
but there are people
you're going to learn to care about.
I realize I see this as the problem
with putting Subnautica on a talk.
I'll talk about it forever.
To skip through this,
let's just say that there are 5 to 8
non-player characters that you see
within Crow country,
and the way that the written you do
get to care about all of them.
They do have their own community
that they form.
They have a lot of thoughts
about each other, about how they act.
You can't save them all, but there are
five that you can get at the end.
But the real community
that you're dealing with is the guests.
And here's where I'm just going to say
very briefly that if you've not played
Crow Country Mute for about five minutes,
my apologies for this,
because the most interesting thing
happens at the end,
which is a pair of subsequent reveals.
And this is where player
agency is very much subverted.
So the first reveal is not unusual
for a horror game.
Of course, the mutated, vaguely
humanoid creatures that you're fighting,
of course, they're actually humans.
Of course
that's that's where we're going with this.
So that's not going to hit
hard for a horror game player.
The second reveal after
that is where those humans come from.
And this is where the game
is subverting agency,
because you have the first reveal
of everything that you fought and killed
and tried very hard not to die to.
Everything you've decimated over
the course of the game
was actually a human being
that maybe potentially could be saved.
The second reveal is that those humans
are actually coming from the future.
The game takes place in 1990.
They are coming from the year 2106,
and they are essentially coming back
to the year 1990
to try to prevent a major catastrophe
that's happened in the future.
This game is not subtle
about climate change, and it's not subtle
about the fact that the reason
those humans are coming through
mutated is because of things
that are happening in 1990.
But the point that matters here
is that you, the player, you can't fix it,
which is a huge subversion of agency
and games.
We are trained that all problems
are solvable and all problems are ours
to solve.
And the whole idea that there's
this massive problem in the future,
like normally
we would be the ones to deal with that.
The developers have said about
Crow Country that it is in some ways
a game about being born
just too late to save the world.
And again,
when we get to the very end of it,
which I'll just skip to with this slide,
what you see is the five people
that have managed to come out,
including the player,
and none of them are happy about it
because we've survived
this one moment of horror.
But we know what's coming,
and we know we are
not only unable to stop it,
but have been unable to stop it.
And again, it's centered
not just to round those five characters
and not even about the larger
group of characters in the amusement park,
but about the community of humanity
as a whole.
So, briefly,
the reason that I care about this
is that I am consistently interested
in the kinds of stories that are best
or only told through interactive media
and through the medium of games.
And one of the things
that's interesting about horror games
specifically, and indie horror
in this particular case,
is how we're not now pulling from film
or from cinema from other places,
but looking at how we can actually scare
the player effectively through mechanics
and through agency.
And I'm really interested to see how
these indie horror games are doing that.
And that is now
at the end of this part of this talk.
Thank you very, very much.